Guide to the William J. Cassidy Files on the Tri-State Mining District of Missouri, Kansas and Oklahoma TAM.063
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
William J. Cassidy Files on the Tri-State Mining District of Missouri, Kansas and Oklahoma
1925-1950
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Cassidy, William J.
TAM.063
0.5 Linear Feet (1 box)
The collection contains letters and interview notes from persons involved in lead and zinc mining describing early attempts at unionization; copies of contracts between operators and locals of the International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers, CIO, mostly dating to the 1940s; clippings, and mining industry and government pamphlets on mining conditions. The material was collected by William J. Cassidy while he was writing his University of Pittsburgh doctoral dissertation completed in 1955.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by William J. Cassidy, 1969. The accession number associated with this gift is 1969.002.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
William J. Cassidy compiled these materials in the course of researching and writing his doctoral dissertation, "The Tri-State Zinc-Lead Mining Region: Growth, Problems and Prospects" (University of Pittsburgh, 1955).
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains letters and interview notes from persons involved in lead and zinc mining in the Tri-State Mining District (Kansas, Missouri, Oklahoma); describing early attempts at unionization, copies of contracts between operators and locals of International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers, CIO; printed ephemera from the union and several of its locals, mostly dating to the 1940s; clippings; mining industry and government pamphlets on mining conditions and a manuscript, "History of International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers Union Local 15," by Harry Blasser.
Arrangement
The folders are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into one series:
Missing Title
I, Research Files, 1925-1950.
Correspondence.; Interviews.; Notes.; Pamphlets.; Missouri |x Social conditions.; Oklahoma |x Social conditions.; Clippings (information artifacts); Collective labor agreements.; Lead miners |z United States.; Kansas |x Social conditions.; Zinc mines and mining |z United States.; Blasser, Harry. History of International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers Union Local 15.; Cassidy, William J.; International Union of Mine, Mill, and Smelter Workers; Tri-State Mining District; International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers. Local 15 (Picher, Okla.); Cassidy, William J.
- Series I: Research Files, 1925-1950.
  - Blasser, Harry, "History of International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers Local 15", Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Cassidy, William J.: Correspondence, 1947, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cassidy, William J.: Research Notes and Interview with Melvin H. Black, M.D., Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Cherokee County (Kansas) Health Department Second Annual Report, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Harbaugh, M. D.: "Labor Relations in the Tri-State Mining District." Mining Congress Journal, Jun 1936 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Harbaugh, M. D.: "The Tri-State Zinc and Lead Mining District in 1935." Mining Congress Journal, Feb 1936 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hubbell, A. H. "Survey of Mining Practice 1951." Engineering and Mining Journal (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers: Printed Ephemera, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers. Research Department, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers. Local 856. Collective Labor Agreements., 1947 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Midwest Research Institute. Chemistry Division. "A Survey and Scientific Analysis of the Natural Resources and Industrial Potential of the Greater Joplin (Mo.) Area, Jan 5, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Mine, Mill vs. CIO Fight Means Turmoil in Mining. Reprinted from Engineering and Mining Journal, Apr 1950 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Shaner, Dolph: Tri-State Area Local History Pamphlets, 1925-1944 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Statements of Witnesses, Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Tri-State Miner, Vol. 1., no. 1, May 31, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Tri-State Zinc and Lead Ore Producers Association: Statement to…Frances Perkins…On Living and Working Conditions, Aug 23, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 17)